Guide to the Letters to Ernst Curtius and Ernst Robert Curtius, 1841-1956.
Letters to Ernst Curtius and Ernst Robert Curtius
- Series 2: Letters to Ernst Robert Curtius
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 3 December 1929; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 90)
    ALS in French: René Schwob, Charles Du Bos...
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 4 December 1929; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 91)
    ALS in French: Curtius's next sojourn in France.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 21 January 1930; 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 92)
    ALS in French: Curtius's marriage; André Siegfried, Edouard Bourdet, Maurice Barrès.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 4 February 1930; 1 leaf + 1 postcard (Box 1, Folder 93)
    ALS in French: Curtius's marriage; Gide.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 13 February 1930; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 94)
    ALS in French: their friendship, journalism.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 16 February 1930; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 95)
    ALS in French about her readings and correspondence.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 31 March 1930; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 96)
    ALS in French: Proust, Bernard Groethuysen.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [April 1930]; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 97)
    ALS in French: literary honors ("On ne donnerait plus le Prix Nobel à Dante.")
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 26 April 1930; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 98)
    ALS in French: review of Curtius's book in "Le Figaro." With an undated postcard on the same subject.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 14 May 1930; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 99)
    ALS in French, containing a handwritten poem by her, "Nova."
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 1 June 1930; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 100)
    ALS in French (postcard from Vence.)
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 10 June 1930; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 101)
    ALS in French: Edouard Bourdet, James Joyce, France-Allemagne.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, July 1930; 4 leaves (Box 2, Folder 102)
    ALS in French: annotated and corrected proofs for "Un Manuel de civilisation française."
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 16 July 1930; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 103)
    ALS in French: Claude Bourdet and the International Congress of Students in Paris.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 2 August 1930; 4 leaves (Box 2, Folder 104)
    ALS in French: Europe, China.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 24 August 1930; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 105)
    ALS in French: Paulhan's decision not to hire her as scientific journalist for the "NRF."
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 4 October 1930; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 106)
    ALS in French: Herrad von Landsberg.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 14 October 1930; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 107)
    ALS in French: reception of Curtius in France.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 3 January 1931; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 108)
    ALS in French: Sieburg's "Dieu est-il français ?" (Grasset, 1930)
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 18 January 1930; 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 109)
    ALS in French: Sieburg's "Dieu est-il français ?" (Grasset, 1930); project of an interview of André Siegfried titled "Contre l'Amérique!"; France and Germany.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 14 February 1930; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 110)
    ALS in French: health problems; Vence.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. [1931]; 3 leaves (Box 2, Folder 111)
    ALS in French: body and soul; Diderot and Montaigne.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 8 June 1931; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 112)
    ALS in French about Gnosticism and Christianism ("Nous sommes catholiques, ER!")
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, September 1931; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 113)
    ALS in French: the spirit of the Middle Ages and the present time.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, October 1931; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 114)
    ALS in French: news of her son Claude; her readings: Racine, Corneille.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 18 November 1931; 1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 115)
    ALS in French and English. With a poem in German, "Todwasser," composed by her son Claude Bourdet.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 4 December 1931; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 116)
    ALS in German and French.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, December 1931; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 117)
    ALS in German: vacations in Vence and in the Alps.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, December 1931; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 118)
    ALS in French and German: "Comment ne verrais-je pas l'Allemagne à travers vous? Elle vous a fait. Sa jeunesse vous lit et vous écoute..."
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, January 1932; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 119)
    ALS in French: writings and readings (Jules Romains, Stefan George); friendship with Marie Kiener; her Italian origins.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 31 January 1932; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 120)
    ALS in French: her translations of Lucretius.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, February 1932; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 121)
    ALS in French: relation of a dinner with the Nietzsche scholar [and Nazi sympathiser] Friedrich Würzbach and René Schwob, "le Boswell de Gide."
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 5 February 1932; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 122)
    ALS in French: St Paul, Maritain...
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 11 February 1932; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 123)
    ALS in French: Tibullus, Colette...
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, mid-February 1932; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 124)
    ALS in French: André Siegfried, Italy...
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 21 February 1932; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 125)
    ALS in French about metaphysics.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 27 February 1932; 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 126)
    ALS in French: philosophy and science.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 8 March 1932; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 127)
    ALS in French: her writings and interest in science.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 14 March 1932; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 128)
    ALS in French: the death of her mother.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, end of March1932; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 129)
    ALS in French: "Suivre votre travail aura été le dernier plaisir d'un certain moi appliqué au monde."
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 26 May 1932; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 130)
    ALS in French: her travels in Europe.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 16 June 1932; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 131)
    ALS in French: despair.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 9 September 1932; 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 132)
    ALS in French and German: her property in Dordogne.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 26 December1932; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 133)
    ALS in German.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 22 January 1933; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 134)
    ALS in French: Proust, Benda...
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 26 January1932; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 135)
    ALS in French: the task of the cleric, the importance of erudition...
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 5 February 1933; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 136)
    ALS in French: chronology and style.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 13 July 1933; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 137)
    ALS in German: news from the house, her son...
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 9 October 1933; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 138)
    ALS in German: considerations about life, the animals...
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 31 October 1933; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 139)
    ALS in French ("Vous voulez que je vous écrive en français"): her mood and writings.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 31 October 1933; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 140)
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 17 November 1933; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 141)
    ALS in French: their correspondence; Curtius's "Balzac."
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 30 December 1933; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 142)
    ALS in French and ancient Greek: her friends in Paris (Abel Bonnard, Jacques Maritain); the correspondence with Rilke.
  - Pozzi, Catherine, to E.R. Curtius, 20 february 1934; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 143)
    ALS in French: "Je vais entreprendre de vous écrire avec un stylo cassé." Annotated by Curtius: "letzter Brief."
  - Rambaud, Henri, to E.R. Curtius, 18 March 1933; 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 144)
    ALS in French: Balzac, Stendhal, Valéry; Curtius's "Essai sur la France."
  - Schlumberger, Jean, to Ilse Curtius, 4 May 1956; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 145)
    ALS in French: condolences.
  - Thibaudet, Albert, to E.R. Curtius, 15 April 1924; 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 146)
    ALS in French about Curtius's essay on Balzac: "Vous avez fait de la critique créatrice, celle qui s'impose quand on a à parler d'un créateur comme Balzac."
  - Thibaudet, Albert, to E.R. Curtius, 22 April 1924; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 147)
    ALS in French: Bergson; Décade de Pontigny.
  - Thibaudet, Albert, to E.R. Curtius, 22 August 1924; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 148)
    ALS in French: sojourns of young French intellectuals (incl. Armand Bérard) in Heidelberg, Germany, at Curtius's invitation.
  - Thibaudet, Albert, to E.R. Curtius, n.d. (1928); 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 149)
    ALS in French: notions of literary critique.
  - Thibaudet, Albert to E.R. Curtius, 30 June 1929; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 150)
    ALS in French about their respective publications.
  - Valéry, Jeannie, to E.R. Curtius, 9 December 1955; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 151)
  - Valéry, Paul, to E.R. Curtius, 24 August 1933; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 152)
    ALS in French. Responding to a pressing request made by Curtius to employ German scholars who would otherwise be facing persecution by the Nazi regime, Paul Valéry explains why, in his capacity as the general administrator of the "Centre Universitaire Méditerranéen" in Nice, he is unfortunately unable to do anything: his authority is limited by government regulations as well as by financial constraints; an academic center is not a university, and therefore can offer only lectures to visiting faculty, not regular teaching; there are no professorial chairs, unless foreign governments wish to endow them, etc.